If you've ever played peekaboo and felt like your baby somehow knew
what was coming, that intuition is backed by real developmental
psychology.
Long before babies can talk, they're already predicting social
patterns, detecting cause and effect, and storing simple memories of
new actions.
In this video, I'll walk through four classic infant experiments you
can adapt at home, and how to do them without turning a playful
observation into an overblown conclusion.
First, the big caveat: these are not diagnostic tests.
A single home session cannot tell you whether your baby is advanced,
delayed, or anything in between. Think of these as carefully observed
games.
For all four, use the same ground rules: choose a calm, alert baby,
keep the room quiet, stop if your baby fusses, and keep the session
short.
Experiment one is peekaboo, but done as a real protocol.
In the 1970s, Bruner argued that peekaboo works because it has a rigid
structure: disappearance, suspense, and reveal. That gives babies
something to predict.
At home, keep the script identical for three or four trials: eye
contact, the same ready cue, cover, pause two seconds, then reveal.
Once that baseline is stable, change one thing. Delay the reveal.
Reveal from the wrong side.
What you're watching for is anticipation: a smile before the reveal,
body tension during the pause, or eyes going where they expected you.
The point is not that your baby understands the game. It's that even
this simple social routine is giving them a structure they can learn
and predict.
Experiment two is the still-face paradigm, and this one is optional
because it's the most sensitive.
Tronick's classic finding was that when a normally responsive parent
suddenly goes neutral and unresponsive, babies protest quickly.
The home version is simple: one minute of normal warm play, up to
thirty seconds of still face, then immediate reunion.
If your baby cries, turns red, or if you feel uncomfortable, stop
right away. The reunion is not optional.
It shows that by four to five months, babies already expect social
partners to respond contingently. When that pattern breaks, they
notice.
Experiment three may be the most visually rewarding.
In the classic studies, babies learned that kicking made something
happen overhead. At home, the safest version uses a floor play gym and
full hands-on supervision.
First, watch two minutes of normal kicking with no connection. Then
add a loose connection so kicking moves the toy. Then remove it again.
The observation lives in the contrast between phases. Does kicking
become more deliberate when the toy responds? Do you see a burst after
disconnect?
That's contingency detection: noticing that when I do this, that
happens. It's remarkable on its own. You don't need to inflate it.
Experiment four is imitation, and here the careful version matters.
The flashy claim that newborns imitate faces has not held up well. The
stronger evidence comes a little later, with object actions.
Start with the easiest version: perform an unusual action with a
rattle three times, then hand it over and wait silently. A partial
copy counts.
For older babies, add a short delay: demonstrate, put the object away,
do something else for ten minutes, then bring it back with no
reminder.
What matters is not perfect copying. It's whether your baby retained
some representation of the action they saw.
The difference between a home experiment and random play is how you
write it down.
Record what you saw, not what you think it means. "Baby kicked more"
is an observation. "Baby understood cause and effect" is
interpretation.
Timing, temperament, and sheer luck are huge confounders. A single
trial is interesting. A pattern across different days is much more
informative.
What I love about these experiments is not that they prove something
grand. It's that they make early cognition visible.
Peekaboo lets you watch prediction. Still-face reveals social
expectation. Kick-to-move shows cause and effect. Imitation gives you
a glimpse of memory.